<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Pope, and all his cardinals, bishops, Jesuits, monks and friars, with all the rest of his people, who are reprobates concerning the faith of Christ, gospel-order, and true religion, and also the papists prov'd to be a seditious sect being something in answer to Æneas Mach. Gilmury, and Mauritius Bern, who call themselves students of art / J.L. J.S.</title>
            <author>Lancaster, James, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9411</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11808930</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11808930</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49487</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49487)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 540:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Pope, and all his cardinals, bishops, Jesuits, monks and friars, with all the rest of his people, who are reprobates concerning the faith of Christ, gospel-order, and true religion, and also the papists prov'd to be a seditious sect being something in answer to Æneas Mach. Gilmury, and Mauritius Bern, who call themselves students of art / J.L. J.S.</title>
                  <author>Lancaster, James, d. 1699.</author>
                  <author>Stubbs, John, 1618?-1674.</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By James Lancaster and John Stubbs. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Postscript signed: G.</note>
                  <note>G. is George Fox. Cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gilmury, Aeneas Mach.</term>
               <term>Bern, Mauritius.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49487:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49487:1"/>
            <p>TO THE POPE, And All His Cardinals, Biſhops, Jeſuits, Monks, and Friars, with all the reſt of his People;</p>
            <p>Who are Reprobates concerning the Faith of Chriſt, Goſpel-Order, and true Religion: And alſo the <hi>Papists</hi> prov'd to be a Seditious Sect.</p>
            <p>BEING Something in Anſwer to <hi>Aeneas Mach. Gilmury,</hi> and <hi>Mauritius Bern;</hi> who call themſelves Students of Art.</p>
            <p>J. L. J. S.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Evil Men and Seducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>As <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do theſe reſiſt the Truth, Men of corrupt Minds, Reprobates concerning the Faith,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>God ſhall ſend them ſtrong Deluſions, that they ſhould believe a Lye, that they all might be damned, who believe not the Truth, but had pleaſure in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Theſ. 2.11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1671.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:49487:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49487:2"/>
            <head>To the POPE, and all his Cardinals, Biſhops, Jeſuits, Monks and Friars, with all the reſt of his People.</head>
            <p>I Have received a Paper, ſubſcribed by <hi>Aeneas</hi> M. <hi>Gillmury</hi> and <hi>Mauritius Bern,</hi> who call themſelves Students of Arts, and both Profeſſors of the <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> and <hi>Roman Catholique</hi> Church; which is a pretended Anſwer to <hi>John Stubbs,</hi> and <hi>James Lancaſter,</hi> their Quaeries and Challenges, they ſent to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> and his <hi>Cardinals</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But all people may ſee that this is not an Anſwer, but inſtead of anſwering, they beg the Queſtion; and fall a railing, and ſometimes Daub and Flatter, thinking by their daubing and flattering to put out the Eyes of their ſimple deluded people. And theſe two Papiſts ſeem to be much grieved, becauſe our Challenge is directed to the Pope, and his Cardinals, and Jeſuits: They find fault with our Long-windedneſs, or ſounding a Trumpet as a Horn; which well we may do, to alarum the Pope, his Jeſuits, and Cardinals: For we muſt tell them, that we have the Breath of the Almighty (which will reach to <hi>Rome</hi>) by which we come to be living Souls.</p>
            <p>And did not the Jeſuits and Prieſts ſay in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that they had no Licenſe from the Pope to anſwer us; and now we have alarum'd the Pope, and Cardinals, and Friars, and Jeſuits; it is well that he doth confeſs this is Long-windedneſs, over their muddy breath.</p>
            <p>And now they tell us, that they can anſwer at Home, and that we need not ſend to the Pope; but no Anſwer to our Challenge, as the Reader of our Challenge and this Paper, may ſee that their Mouths are ſtopt, and that they cannot maintain their own corrupt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor ſeditious Sect.</p>
            <p>And as for your ſaying, that you are both Profeſſors of the <hi>Roman-Catholique</hi> Church, this is falſe; for the <hi>Roman-Catholique</hi> Church,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49487:3"/>as it was in the Apoſtles dayes, you are degenerated from, and are come to be a Seditious Sect, and do ſpread your Heretical Opinions from your Hereſies, which you have at <hi>Rome;</hi> and are a Schiſm and Schiſmatical, rent from the Catholique Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as it was in the Apoſtles Dayes (for <hi>Catholique</hi> we do underſtand is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi>) and are erred from that Univerſal Power, and Faith, and Goſpel, and Spirit, that the Apoſtles were in, you are erred from; as eaſie is to be proved.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt, You the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are a Seditious Sect, with all her company; and you are found in <hi>Herod,</hi> a Perſecutor; you are found in <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> a Burner, by your Fires; you are found in <hi>Judas,</hi> with your Swords and Staves againſt the Juſt; you are found in <hi>Cain,</hi> with your Envy againſt the ſecond Birth <hi>Abel;</hi> you are found in <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> Scoffing at <hi>Iſaac;</hi> you are found to be the Beaſt and the Whore drinking of the Blood of the Saints, that receive not your Mark; So Killing, Burning, Hanging, Racking, Torturing, and Impriſoning; this hath been the work of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who is a Seditious Sect, who are the Traytors, Heady, High-minded, Self-willed, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Pleaſures more then Lovers of God: For look upon your proud Prelates, Cardinals, Jeſuits, Pope, with all his gorgious Robes, theſe are the Wicked Arts, which you have invented, and are Maſters of: So its clear, that all theſe Works be the Works of the fleſh, and of the Devil, that bloody wicked Perſecutor, and not of the Birth born of the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, So I ſay, Here it's clear you are a Seditious Sect, erred from the Faith that works by Love; for if you were in that Catholique Faith, which belongs to the Catholique Church, which is univerſal, you would not tell People of a <hi>Purgatory</hi> when they are dead, for which you have no Scripture; we Challenge you to bring a Scripture for it, out of your own Bibles, or Proteſtants either. And ſo it is clear here by the ſecond Proof, you are erred from the Faith that works by Love, that purifies the heart, that gives Victory and Acceſs to God, by which Faith men pleaſe God, which is the Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of Gods Elect; from this Faith, which is <hi>Catholique,</hi> from which the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with his Company are erred, and are found in the Enmity, Madneſs, Folly, and Perſecution, who are Synagogues of Satan, that Murderer, whoſe works ye have done, and are void of the Faith that works by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49487:3"/>love, and purifies the heart; therefore you muſt have a <hi>Purgatery</hi> as you ſay.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, You are a Seditious Sect; for you have tranſgreſſed the Command of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>Love one another, Love Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> and if any go from you, you will hate them, you will kill them; and if others will not joyn to you, you will burn them and deſtroy them; this is the work of a ſeditious Sect, and <hi>Hammon</hi> like, that informed againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> that did not follow the National way; and like thoſe that informed againſt <hi>Daniel:</hi> And ſo it is clear that you are a ſeditious Sect, erred from the Command of Chriſt Jeſus, and caſt it behind your Backs.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, You are a Company of Lyars, and a Seditious Sect; for how can you love God, whom you never ſee, and hate your Brethren, whom you ſee daily?</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, You are in the death of old <hi>Adam,</hi> and in the power of death the Serpent, who love not your Brother; he that hateth his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abideth in Death.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, You are a Seditious Sect; for you have perſecuted people about Meats, Drinks, Cloths, and outward Croſſes, your Crucifixes, your Bread, and Wine, and Holy-dayes, your eating of Fleſh, and Fiſh, and Marriages, which the Kingdom of God ſtands not in; not Meats, nor Drinks, nor Dayes; but in Righteouſneſs, in Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt; and ſo out of the Power of God, our of this Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, are you all a ſedititiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sect, and are found in thoſe things the Kingdom of God ſtands not in, and Perſecuting and Murdering ſuch as will not obſerve your wills: like to the Beaſt ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that with his Paw would pluck all under him; and like the Dragon, his Wrath is found in you againſt the true Woman, the Church; and they that have followed your Worſhip, have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Dragons worſhip, and the Beaſt, and have not followed Chriſt Jeſus, nor the true <hi>Cath lique Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7thly, You are a Seditious Sect, that teach the Doctrine of Devils forbidding Meats, and to Marry, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. which the Spirit did ſay expreſly ſhould come in the laſt times; who ſpeak Lyes in Hypocriſie, having you Conſciences ſeared, as with a hot-Iron, that you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hardned in your Wickedneſs, Seducing Spirits, Doctrine of Devils: For <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Prieſt, and <hi>Aaron</hi> was a Prieſt, and were Married; and the Prophets and Apoſtles had Wives; and Marriage was Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49487:4"/>Ordinance; and Chriſt eſtabliſhed it in the new Covenant, wherein he ſaith, <hi>Whom God joynes together let no man put aſſunder:</hi> So here it is clear, Chriſt the High-Prieſt, made higher then the Heavens, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms Gods Work, which is Marriage, being his joyning; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not you give liberty to Brothel-Houſes, and Baudy-Houſes, and Uncleanneſs? And then you have need of a Purgatory.</p>
            <p n="8">8thly; You are a Seditious Sect; for you have erred from the Croſs of Chriſt, which is the Power of God, and therefore have you ſet up Wooden Croſſes, and Stone, and Braſs, and Silver, and Gold: And how many Hundred Years after Chriſt were thoſe outward Croſſes invented? And where did ever <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> or any of the Apoſtles ſet up a Wooden Croſs? And ſpeak if you dare: Let us ſee your Antiquity: And how many Hundred Years after Chriſt, got up that Seditious Sect, forbidding Prieſts to Marry, and ſetting up pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to put Women in, and vowed them, and ſwore them to Chaſtity? And how many Hundred Years after Chriſt was it before they made a God, and a Chriſt, of Bread and Wine? Come out of your Holes and Dens, and anſwer us in the Light, if you dare? And try your God and your Chriſt, that you have made of Bread and Wine: See if you will be as Bold as <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts; for they tryed their god before the Prophet: Come, let us ſee what this ſeditious Sect can do with all their Arts; Can you make him Speak? Is he a Living God, that will not be found Aſleep? And will not your Gods grow Corrupt, and Mouldy? And is it not a Work of mans hands, which you call people to Worſhip? Yea, your Fiſts of Wickedneſs, and Bloody Hands, which have been embrued and waſhed in the Blood of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; with thoſe hands have you not made your God, and Chriſt, of your Bread and Wine? And therefore I ſay, come out and try them, &amp; we will have a Bottle of Wine, and a Loaf of Bread, and it ſhall be cut in two pieces, and the Wine in two Baſons; and let the Pope, and his Cardinals, and Friars, and Munks, with all their Bloody Fiſts make a God of part of the Wine, and part of the Bread, and when they have done, we will ſet them in a Cellar with part of the Wine and part of the Bread, which is not conſecrated, and we ſhall try quickly whether their God will not Mould, and their Chriſt will not Dye, that is conſecrated; and their conſecrated Wine grow ſower and dye: Come, ſhuffle us not off; for we will have them locked up in a Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar with ſix or ſeven Locks, and have a Watch on our ſide, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49487:4"/>on yours, and try if your God and your Chriſt, that is made of Bread and Wine do not Corrupt, and do not grow Mouldy; and your Wine doth not grow Sower and Dye; then we will all turn to you, and ſay, that you have made a God and Chriſt by your Art; and then if your God and your Chriſt, you have made of your Bread and Wine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> do grow Mouldy, and the Wine Dye and Sower; your Bread Mouldy that you have conſecrated, you ſhall all turn to us, and acknowledge your ſelves to be a ſeditious Sect, that have been Deceivers of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple this thouſand Years. We do challenge you, &amp; dare you, the Pope, &amp; his Cardinals, and Jeſuits, to come forth, and try, and bring your God out; all you God-Makers, and Chriſt-Makers of the Popes Crue and Company, the Lord calls for you to come out of your Holts, who have been a company of Blood-thirſty men, who have mingled your invented and idolatrous Sacrifices with the Blood of the Innocent, <hi>Pilate</hi> like; a ſeditious Sect, erred from the words of God, and from Chriſt Jeſus the Head of the Church; and therefore you have inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Head, a counterfeit Head of your own making, which is not a <hi>Catholick</hi> Head, but a Seditious Head, full of Sedition, which fills the Body to the brim; you are full of Hypocriſie to the very brim; and full of Envy and Blood-thirſtineſs to the brim; and full of Murder to the very brim; your Actions, your Doings, your Works, your Fruits ſpeak it, and declare it to all Nations about you. But Chriſt Jeſus, he is the Head, the <hi>Cathelique</hi> Head, the Univerſal Head; the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> is Living Members made, and of Living Stones a ſpiritual Houſhold ſanctified by him, and waſhed, and purged, and cleanſed by the Living Head, Chriſt Jeſus, who is the ſame to day, yeſterday, and forever.</p>
            <p n="9">9thly, You are a Seditious Sect; as erred from the Power, from the Spirit of the Apoſtles, and Chriſt Jeſus; and from the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, the fine Linnen, which is the Righteouſneſ, of the Saints, and of Chriſt Jeſus; and therefore you have ſet up your Surplices, and your white Coats, who have loſt your fine Linnen, which is the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt Jeſus, and are more like Actors of Stage-Plays, and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ebancks, (then Preachers of the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all your Fools-Coats, and the Pope and his Cardinals Foolſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caps, Keys, and Crowns: Where do you read in the Scripture, or new Teſtament, of Maſter <hi>Paul,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Peter,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Timothy,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Titus,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Matthew,</hi> or <hi>Luke,</hi> &amp;c. or my Lord <hi>Timothy,</hi> or my Lord
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49487:5"/>
               <hi>Titus,</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> or my Lord Biſhops; we challenge you to make this good out of your own Scripture; let us ſee ſome proof for your Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Pride, who are puft up with Titles, and take the Titles that belong to God Almighty to your ſelves, contrary to <hi>Elihu,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>If I give flattering Titles to men my Maker would not regard me;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chriſt Jeſus, and in deſpite of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>You have one Maſter, and you are his Brethren.</hi> It is very clear that you are a Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sect and Schiſm, and are rent from the Body and the Head both; and therefore you are a Seditious Body: It is you which make ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heads and chriſts, and then ſay, <hi>Lo chriſt is here, and lo he is there;</hi> and your Seditious people run to chriſt-Makers, and god-Makers, or your idol-Makers. Indeed the Heathen Prieſts made gods, which were no Gods; and therefore in <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> and other places, how many gods have you. And how many chriſts have you made in all theſe parts, and chriſt-makers? And then he is here, and there, Lo here, and Lo there, Antichriſt againſt Chriſt: We know that the Devil will rage at this: And how much Blood have you ſhed (number up the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) becauſe they will not eat your gods, and your chriſts, that you have made, and Worſhip it? And is not this worſe then the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then? Did the Heathen eat their gods when they had made them? So it is clear, that you are erred from the <hi>Catholique Croſs,</hi> which is the Power of God; from the <hi>Catholique Faith,</hi> that works by Love; from the <hi>Catholique Head,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus: from the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> the Body of Chriſt Jeſus; and cannot maintain your rudiments, nor your chriſt that you have made, to the Apoſtles days; for did they ſet up any ſuch thing? Your doctrine concerning Purgatory, Meats, Drinks, Holy-dayes, Lent, nor your Cloths; nor your Bell Book and Candle; nor your Popes Head of the Church; none of theſe things can you maintain; nor your Perſecuting about Religion, nor your Maſſ-mongrey-Stuff, nor your ſeveral Orders, nor your Triple-Crowns, nor your Nunneries, nor your Crucifixes, nor your forbidding to Marry, not your Schools of Arts to make Miniſters; none of all theſe things can you make good, that they were acted or practiſed by the Apoſtles, or that they did perſecute any people about outward things.</p>
            <p n="10">10thly, You are a Seditious Sect, and have left the Commands of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>Freely you have received, and Freely give,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49487:5"/>you who have ſet up both Eaſter-Reckonings, and Midſummer-Dues, and Tythes, are a Sect that ſerve your ſelves, and not Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; that mind Earthly things, and are Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt; and are gone in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> to Envy; Gainſaying, <hi>Carah,</hi> againſt the true <hi>Church,</hi> and its practice, and run after the Error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for Gifts and Rewards, the Wages of Unrighteouſneſs, Unrighteous Wages; and like to <hi>Flimas</hi> the <hi>Sorcerer;</hi> who ſeek to turn People from the <hi>Catholique Faith,</hi> that works by Love, whoſe Eyes are blind, groping up and down in your Rudiments, and among your Idols, and Inventions of your Fore-fathers, who erred from the true Church: And as for the <hi>Pelagian-Hereſie,</hi> look at home, you <hi>Papiſts:</hi> and as for the <hi>Arians,</hi> you may look at home; for we are none of that ſpirit: Whereas thou giveſt us a Catalogue of ſome that did ſucceed <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Paul;</hi> but thou doeſt not tell us of Pope <hi>Jone,</hi> and make a Catalogue of her that had a Baſtard; nor thou doſt not tell us of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> whom thou calleſt Pope, that ſacrificed to the Heathen <hi>gods,</hi> and denied Chriſt: What will you ſay that theſe were Rebellious Actions? And thou doſt not tell us of <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, ſet up by <hi>Phocas,</hi> that murdered his Maſter <hi>Mauritius</hi> about ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after <hi>Christ,</hi> then began your firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> general Pope: and you may ſay, if you ſhould do ſo, <hi>Satan</hi> would be divided againſt <hi>Satan,</hi> and ſo could not ſtand. You are far from giving freely, who have ſet up ſo many Glebe-land, and Tythes, and I aſter-reckonings, and fat Parſonages, that you might live in the Glory of the World, not like a ſuffering Seed, but that you are Enemies to the ſuffering Seed.</p>
            <p n="11">11thly, You are a Seditious Sect, you have caſt the Royal Law of God behind your backs, which teacheth to do unto others as you would others ſhould do unto you; for would you have others to Burn you, to Hang you, to Impriſon you, becauſe that you do not conform to their Way or Religion: Would you have the <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> to Rack and Torture, and make <hi>Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> for you, and Burn you, and Hang you, becauſe that you do not conform to their Religion, Blind the Royal Law of God, <hi>To do to others as you would have them to do unto you:</hi> Speak plainly if you can or date; or is <hi>Iſhmael</hi> that <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, Cain</hi> the firſt <hi>Perſecutor of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Nebuchadnezar,</hi> and <hi>Hammon,</hi> and the <hi>Murdering Jews</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> the <hi>Dragon,</hi> become <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> Are not you ſound in this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the brim? And was this divine? <hi>Cain</hi> was a mighty man in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49487:6"/>Arts, as high as you; and ſo was <hi>Nimrod</hi> in his Building, but God confounded him, and his Works, and ſo he will do yours; it is all under the Chain together, with the Workmen: And are not you more like to the proud <hi>Phariſees,</hi> with their long Robes, that love to be called of men Maſter, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Gratious Lords, who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Praiſe of men, and Honour one of another; a Mark of no Believer: Is not this Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, and theſe things, forbidden by Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? See <hi>John</hi> 5. But I muſt tell you, in your Catalogue you ſay that many did ſucceed <hi>Peter:</hi> Where do you read, that in all his time he was called Gratious Lord, or Pope; or that <hi>Timothy,</hi> or <hi>Titus,</hi> or any other, that he was ſet up above another, by the Apoſtles: Did not <hi>Paul</hi> reprove <hi>Peter</hi> for ſome things: This makes nothing for the Pope (the Catalogue you have brought) neither doth it ſuit the matter; for your whole Church, as you call it, together with your Head the Pope, is judged by Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, and the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church; and therefore becauſe that you have loſt the Key of <hi>David,</hi> and Tongue of the Learned, the Pope muſt have the outward Key, and you muſt have the Tongues that begin at <hi>Babel,</hi> which your Brother <hi>Pilate</hi> ſet on the top of Chriſt when he Crucified him; and therefore muſt ſtuddy Arts, and ſo <hi>Tubal Cain;</hi> and this proves you a Seditious Sect, and have loſt the Crown of Life, and therefore he muſt ſet up 3. <hi>Crowns</hi> on his head, a Triple-crown; this becomes the old Fool, that is erred from the Spirit that maketh wiſe, and gives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding he is far ſhort of them that ſaid, <hi>An outward Crown did not become a Preacher of the Goſpel:</hi> Let him look the Hiſtory, and ſee if he can ſind ſuch a one in the <hi>Church-Hiſtory,</hi> before the Pope was: But his Head muſt be beyond <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> Head of Gold; for he ſets a <hi>Tripple-crown</hi> upon h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>bead:</hi> But there is a Stone cut out of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain without hands, that will daſh his Head of Gold to pieces, with his Crown. So it is not the handy works of mens hands, make them never ſo ſtrong, that will ſtand before this Stone: Glory to God in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt forever. And this Stone will become a great Mountain, and fill the whole Earth; it is encreaſing, and in vain do the Pot-ſhreds of the Earth, and Briars, and Thorns, ſet themſelves in Battel-array againſt it; for his Enſign and Flag of Defiance againſt all Idolatry, with their Idols, is hell forth: and his Truth ſpreads, and his Light ſhines, by which they all ſee the Foundation, and Rock of Ages: And this Stone is fallen upon your Head and Body, and will grind you to Powder;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49487:6"/>for when your Head is dead, you make another with a great deal of quarrel and ſtrife, and many times Blood is ſhed, that ſome of your Members are killed about making of a head, when the body makes him like to frantick men that have loſt their Brains: But for your Racks, &amp; Fires, and Fagots, your rude Rabble would never be kept in order; for that noble Spirit and noble Mind of Chriſt Jeſus, the Heavenly Man, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> that rebuked his Diſciples, that would have had Fire to come down from Heaven to conſume them, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did, that would not receive them; and Chriſt told them, that they knew not what ſpirit they were of, that would have had mens lives taken away, and deſtroy them; and this was by way of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Shall we Pray that Fire come down, &amp;c.</hi> Now if they did not know what ſpirit they were of the Diſciples of <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> who would have Fire to come down to conſume the People, they would not do it by Inquiſitians, and outward Burnings, by Stacks of Faggots, nor Hang, ing of them, as you have done: Therefore have you known what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit you are of? Have you known your own ſpirits, either Pope, or Cardinal, or Friars, &amp;c. that have burned, and racked, and put to Death ſo many Thouſands ſince the Apoſtles dayes, ſince you got up with your counterfeit Church and Heads. And ſo you that do not know what ſpirit you are of your ſelves, do you think that any that know God or Chriſt will truſt their bodies, or their ſouls, or ſpirits in your hands, that do not know what ſpirit you are of your ſelves? Then they may ſay they have loſt their Reaſon, and Underſtanding, like your ſelves: But Chriſt's Propheſie is come upon you, &amp; <hi>John</hi>'s Revelation; and the Apoſtles, That the Man of ſin and Son of perdition is exalted above all that is called God in you; and ſo there might be a ceparting away from Truth, and then the man of ſin ſhould be revealed and there muſt be a falling away; and ſo he is revealed now, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2, but the Lord will conſume him with the Breath of his Mouth, and deſtroy him with the Brightneſs of his coming, that Satan, that hath been working in you, all thoſe lying Signs and Wonders, with the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vableneſs of Unrighteouſneſs, in you that Periſh, becauſe you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not the Love of the Truth, that you might be ſaved: For this cauſe God hath ſent ſtrong Deluſions among you, that you ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Lye, that they might be damned who believe not the Truth, but have had pleaſure in all your unrighteous doings, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions and bloodthirſtineſs: But we are bound to give God Thanks always
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49487:7"/>through Jeſus Chriſt who hath called us by his Goſpel to obtain the Glory of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Head of our Church: But It's clear you are of them that have ſmitten your Fellow-Servants, and have eaten and drunken with the Drunkards: for what muſt you look for? but to be cut aſſunder, and appointed your Portion with Hypocrites, where is Weeping and Gnaſhing of Teeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. And you have made ſalfe chriſts, and ſhewed your Signs and Wonders, if it were poſſible, to deceive the very Elect; but it is not poſſible; the Elect was before the World was: And ſo you are the unprofitable Servants, that have hid your Tallent (the fruit of which is Love) under your earthly Traditions, your earthly Idols and Rudiments, your own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and Works of your own hands: and the fear you teach your people, is by your own precepts, which you never had from God, Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles; and inſtead of Clothing the Naked, and Feeding the Hungry, and Receiving Strangers, and Viſiting the Sick, you have made Naked, you have made Sick, you have made Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; and in as much as you have done it to theſe true Chriſtians, you have done it to Chriſt the Head: And why? Becauſe they will not own your Idolatrous Wayes and Idols, your counterfeit Head, your counterfeit Church; and inſtead of Viſiting in Priſon, you have caſt into Priſon, and there let them Periſh: Hear the Sentence of the Head of the Church for all your evil doings and works, <hi>Depart from me; for you muſt go into everlaſting Puniſhment; yea, depart from me, ye cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> Then, what have you got here by all your Merits, by all your Works, your tinckling Cymbals, your founding Braſs, who have not had love? Have you given your Goods to the Poor? Could you give your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be Burned? Have you Tongues, <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> and full of Envy and Blood-thirſtineſs, and void of Love? A ſeditious Sect, degenerated: Have you Faith? It's but a dead one, one that doth not work by Love; for Love is the fulfilling of the Law: Is not the Birth of the Fleſh ſound amongſt you, of <hi>Hagar,</hi> that perſecutes him that is born of the Spirit, the Free-womans Children: And ſo are not you the diſhonourable Birth, that muſt be caſt out? And are not the works of the Fleſh manifeſt amongſt you, as, <hi>Adultery, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſciviouſneſs, Idolatry, Witch-craft, Hatred, Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Emulations, Wrath, Strife Sedition, Hereſie, Envy, Murder, Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs, Revilling,</hi> &amp; ſuch like? Look upon your church, are not all theſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49487:7"/>found? Look over <hi>Ireland</hi> on your Holy-dayes; what <hi>Drunkeneſs;</hi> I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw ſo many people drunk, as I do of your people, on that you call <hi>Peter</hi>'s-day; but the fruits of the ſpirit it is <hi>Love, Joy, Peace, Gentleneſs, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Meekneſs, Goodneſs, Long ſuffering, Faith, Temperance;</hi> but theſe are wanting among you, and the other Fruits plentifully may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered of your corrupt Trees, that cannot bring forth good Fruit; who are Strangers to the Covenant of Promiſe, without the Hope that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies as he is pure; therefore you muſt have a Purgatory when you are dead: and ſo are like a Company of Heathen Prieſts, raging for your Images, and your Idols, and your godds, you have made of Bread and Wine, and chriſts; and are ignorant of them that preach the true Doctrine of the Apoſtles, who preached the Word in the Heart and Mouth; and Chriſt was in people, except they were Reprobates, though they have had Bread and Wine: The Apoſtles tell people no where that Bread and Wine was Chriſt, after they had bleſſed it; the Apoſtle tells them of an Anointing within them, that ſhould teach them, and as it doth teach them, they ſhould continue in the Son and in the Father, and as he was, ſo were they in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent evil World: So they need not have a Purgatory, but you are all in your Purgatories already, Head and Tail, and Body, already ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from God, and the true Church, and Head; And ſo as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Falſe Prophets ſhould come,</hi> Mat. 7.2., <hi>and Antichrists;</hi> and bid the Diſciples not to go after them, <hi>for they ſhould be inwardly ravening Wolves, having Sheeps-Clothing:</hi> And ſo its clear that you have the Sheeps-clothing, that you are inwardly ravening Wolves, that have worried ſo many Sheep and Lambs; but you have prey'd upon them, and made War with the Remnant of the Seed of the Woman, and have drunk the Blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus So as Chriſt ſaid they ſhould come, and <hi>John</hi> ſaid they were come, and it was the laſt time then, and they went forth into the World, and the World went after them; and ſo you were the Fore-men of the World, that led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Error, as you may read in <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21. A dread <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> where the ſpirit ſpeaks expreſly in the latter dayes of forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Marriage, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, the doctrine of Devils: And read <hi>Jude,</hi> ſuch as ſhould go in <hi>Cain</hi>'s way, and <hi>Balaam</hi>'s way, and <hi>Corah</hi>'s way, gainſaying the Goſpel, perſecuting for Gifts and Rewards; and here your Fruits are clearly ſeen, the Son of Righteouſneſs ſhines over your heads amongſt his Peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; and ſo here you went from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49487:8"/>Head, Chriſt; if you had been of them, no doubt but you would have continued with them; Chriſt ſaw you inwardly ravening from the Spirit of God, from the Spirit of Truth, the Word of God in the Heart; from the true Faith, that works by Love; from the true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and ſo are up to the very brim in falſe doctrine, and Idols, and Images of your own making, and Inventions; and ſo you may ſee in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> how the Beaſts got up; the firſt out of the Sea, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond out of the Earth; and how the Dragon gave his Power to the Beaſt, and how his Worſhip was ſet up; and how the Whore the falſe Church got up, and there are the Names of the Beaſt, which we leave you to interpret; and how long the Beaſt muſt be worſhipped: and how long the true Church was to be in the Wilderneſs, and to be fed of God, and the Man-Child taken up to God, and he ſhould be brought forth again, and to rule all Nations with a Rod of Iron; and the Bride ſhould come forth again, and the Marriage of the Lamb ſhould be known again, and the Lamb and the Saints ſhould have the Victory: So read your Antiquity, and how that all that would not receive the Beaſt's Mark, and drink the Whores Cup; the falſe-church ſhe drunk the Blood of the Saints: What, hath ſhe been as a Queen, and hath ſhe ſeen no ſorrow? But now is ſhe loſing her Children; and the Scripture is fulfilling, Glory be to the Lord God forever. But you ſhall cry, Alas, Alas, What have we had a Golden Cup, that is full of Abomination? What have your Kings drunk it, and do ſome begin to hate her? Oh! You muſt drink the Cup of the fierceneſs of the Wrath of God Almighty, before this cup of Abomination be purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of you: The Angels begin to ſound their Trumpets; and the Everlaſting Goſpel is preached a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain, and that makes you to roar; it ſounds to <hi>Rome,</hi> and to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and to the <hi>Maguls,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles:</hi> the Everlaſting Power of God, before the Devil was, will awaken you: The Goſpel-Bell begins to Ring, it is beyond <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Bells; Chriſt, the High-Prieſt, is entring into his Temple. For, had you been of the Apoſtles, no doubt but you would have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued with them; for your doctrine is forbid by Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; for Chriſt bid, <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed my Lambs.</hi> And you Wolves worry them, and have got the Sheep. Clothing in three or four Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, you have learned naturally; and they that had the gift of Tongues were but tinckling Cymbals and ſounding Braſs, who had not love; and therefore all your Sounds, it hath been but in compariſon the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49487:8"/>ſound of Braſs, and your tinckling but as Cymbals, and your own Inventions: And ſo your head is falſe, not being found of that <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Faith,</hi> that works by Love: And the Word of the Lord God is kindling, that Fire that will burn the Whores Fleſh, and will take her, together with the Beaſt, and the Dragon, and caſt her and them alive into the Lake of Fire.</p>
            <p>What, you to profeſs Chriſt Jeſus in words, and Murder and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to death! What is this but <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Heathens</hi> ſpirit and nature; and the Whore, and the Beaſt, and the Dragon, and the Devil, and falſe Prophets, and falſe Apoſtles, and Antichriſt againſt the true Apoſtle and Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>Love Enemies, Love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Seditious Sect! For when the ſecond Beaſt roſe out of the Earth, then all your earthly Idols were eſtabliſhed, earthly Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, earthly Images; and then got your Whore on the top of the Beaſt, your falſe Church, Myſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> arrayed in Purple and Scarlet, deckt with Gold and Precious-Stones, and Pearls; do you ſee how ſhe is decked? a Golden Cup in her hand, full of Abomination, of Filthineſs, of Fornication; and upon her head written, <hi>Myſtery Babylon the great, the Mother of Harlots:</hi> Yea, of all the Harlots from God, from Chriſt, from the Apoſtles, from the Spirit, from the Faith, from the Truth, from the Power of God, the Croſs of Chriſt, from the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and from Chriſt the true Head, and from the true Church: And this Whore thus decked, has drunk the Blood of the Saints, and Jeſus his Martyrs: Who cannot but wonder to ſee ſuch a Monſter! And from whence came he, that this Whore, this Woman, this falſe Church ſits upon, but from the Bottomleſs-pit; and thither muſt they return again, with his Horns.</p>
            <p>And now is the Cry is, <hi>Come out of her my People;</hi> ſignifying that God hath a People to come out there, leſt they be Partakers of her Plagues, This is the day that the Lord is calling, Come out of her my People; we have heard his Voice, and can rejoyce over her; for God will be avenged on her, and ſhe ſhall be caſt down like a mighty Mill-ſtone, read <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. For mark, Here is the Devil, the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and the Whore, and the falſe Prophet as Companions, that came out of the Beaſt like Froges. Theſe go altogether; to wit, the Beaſt, and the Dragon, and the Whore on the top of the Beaſt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49487:9"/>the Dragons Power, and his worſhip hath been ſet up, and ſhe is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the Devils power, killing and murdering the Lord Jeſus his Martyrs, and Prophets.</p>
            <p>What! Hath your Church lived deliciouſly, and been as a Queen, and no Widdow? Doth ſhe profeſs to be a Married Wife, and a Queen? She hath made many of her Merchants rich, and is not ſhe become the Habitation of Devils, and Hold of every foul ſpirit, and Cage of every hateful Bird? And hath not the Beaſt had two Horns, like a Lamb, and exerciſed the power of the firſt Beaſt; and all that will not worſhip, and receive h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Image, and drink the Whores Cup, muſt be made war againſt, and their Blood drunk? The Son of Righteouſneſs is riſen, that ſhines, that ſhews his Horns, his Marks, his Names, &amp; what is written upon the Whores Fore-head: and ſo againſt them that have kept the Teſtimony of Jeſus (the Spirit of Propheſie) by which they have ſeen you, you have made War againſt them, and againſt them that have kept the Commands of God, the Remnant of her Seed, which is the Seed of the Woman, whom the Dragon was wrath withal, and was fled into the Wilderneſs, there to be fed of God one thouſand two hundred ſixty dayes; and this Dragon gave his power to your Beaſt, that the Whore ſits upon; and ſo by the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons power ſhe rules: And out of this Beaſts power have your falſe Prophet gone crooking up and down the Nations, and creeping un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Mountain like Froggs, the unclean ſpirits; and theſe ſpirits are Devils, that came out of the Mouth of the Beaſt and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet that ſhould work Miracles, and deceive the World. But a day of Famine will come, and Plague and Death to this Life that you live in, and flaming Fire; for ſtrong is the Lord God that judgeth her, the great Whore, and falſe Church, her ſmoak is ſeen, and we know that you will begin to knaw your tongues for Pain; for your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is full of Darkneſs: For the Angel hath Power over your Thrones, and your Rivers will be dried up, which is muddy Water. For hath not your City bin divided into three parts, and the <hi>Turk</hi> got one part, and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> another? And all your noiſom Smells begin to ſmell, who have the Beaſts Mark in your Fore-heads, and have worſhipped his Image, that have been out of the Image of Chriſt; and ſo the Lord is True and Righteous in his Judgments; for he hath judged the great Whore, which hath corrupted the Earth with her Forhication and will avenge the blood of his Servants at your hands:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49487:9"/>ſhe hath corrupted the Earth with her Idols, and Idolatries, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and Fables; and ſo we are come through the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, above her, by which we ſee the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the true Spouſe, the Lambs Wiſe, Chriſt the Head, the true Church, and the new Earth, wherein dwells Righteouſneſs; and your old Earth, which the Devil compaſſeth, wherein dwells Unrighteouſneſs, filled with Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and Corruption, and filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, that which cumbers the Ground, fruitleſs Trees that have born no Fruit to God.</p>
            <p>The Gates of our City, Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> are not ſhut neither by Night nor Day; but any that come to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, they may enter through the Light into our City, which is far above your <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> falſe City, falſe Church, VVhore, Dragon, falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, which hath been the Drinker of the Blood of the Righteous; Perſecutors and Murderers by the Devils power and authority, which Chriſt, who is our Head comes to deſtroy, who was before the Devil was, and will be when the Devil is gone; who was Firſt and Laſt; the Beginning, and End; the Top and Corner-Stone, who is our Rock, which our Houſe is built upon; and our Foundation, upon which we are built: Glory to God in the Higheſt for evermore. And now to ſomething further.</p>
            <p>VVhereas you tell us a long Tale of <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> a <hi>Philoſopher;</hi> you have juſt hit your own Condition, for it ſuits your preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and it is a very fit Compariſon for you, who would make Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple believe you can make a godd and chriſt, and make a head for your Body, the POPE; and ſo deceive people; as he makes people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>That the Snow was Black, and the Sun was a broad Plate of Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal:</hi> And ſo you are ſo perverſe in Nature, though you are confuted, and convinced in your Conſciences, you will not be brought from your Error, as before mentioned, and out of your Seditious and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious wayes; and ſo you have gone about to confound Truth, but it is too hard for you; for the Devil is out of it.</p>
            <p>And as for your prophane Impiety, you ſay we draw people to, that is your own Condition, and <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Fables, and <hi>Heathens</hi> alſo, you may find enough of them at home in your own Houſes and Fields; nay worſe then the <hi>Iews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems you cry out, <hi>That we Diſturb the Tranquility of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion:</hi> Nay, it is your falſe Religion, which you have made,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49487:10"/>who are a Seditious Sect, who are erred from the Pure <hi>Religion</hi> that is above, that keeps from the Spots of the World, which is to viſit the Fatherleſs, Widdows, and Strangers; and you inſtead of this caſt into Priſon, and let your Poor go Begging up and down your Streets, and Fatherleſs, and Widdows; as look into <hi>France,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parts: And if you were in this Religion, which you, as a Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sect, are erred from, which would keep you from the Spots of the World, which is pure from above, and undefiled before God, you would not tell people of a <hi>Purgatory:</hi> And ſo the pure <hi>Religion</hi> we ſtand for, againſt all your falſe Ones; and every one among us may Miniſter as they have received the Grace, as <hi>good Stewards;</hi> and they may all Propheſie one by one: And God hath poured out his Spirit upon his Sons, and Daughters, and Hand-maids, and Young-men, and Old men, that every one hath ſomewhat to offer to God; but this is a Strange Paradox to your falſe Church and ſeditious Sect, that are erred from the Apoſtles, who limit your Preaching to ſuch as have got the Natural tongues; and ſo, <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> like, whom you pleaſe you ſet up, and whom you pleaſe you pull down: and whom you pleaſe you open their Mouths, and whom you pleaſe you ſtop them; and they that would not Bow at the ſound of your PIPE and ORGAN, you caſt into the Fire, <hi>Nebuchadnezar like:</hi> But this is a Strange Paradox; you can make Miniſters, as you can make a Chriſt and a Godd, one like the other, out of Truth; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo, in ſo doing deny the true Miniſters, and the true Chriſt, and God, who is to be worſhipped in the Spirit and in the Truth, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſet up above 1600 years ſince; and ſince you have forſaken <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is worſhipped in the <hi>Spirit</hi> and in the <hi>Truth,</hi> you <hi>compel</hi> others; do not you ſo? who is the ſame to day, yeſterday, and forever. But from this Infallible Worſhip, that Chriſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t up in the Spirit and in the Truth (which the Devil is out of) are you erred from the Spirit and Truth, &amp; become a Seditious Sect, an Erronious and Schiſmatical Sect and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the true Worſhippers of the living God in Spirit and Truth, which Truth and Spirit is within, by which Spirit the God of Truth is known. It ſeems <hi>John Stubbs,</hi> and <hi>James Lancaſter,</hi> have ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly angred that Seditious Sect of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas thou telleſt us of <hi>Phanatick Aſſertions,</hi> which we are clear of; but thou mayſt look at home for that, and take in thy old fathers Puddles of Errors and Blaſphemies, which we deny: And
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49487:10"/>as for <hi>Phanatick,</hi> is there a People more like them in the World then you, in Rage, and Fury, and Madneſs againſt the Righteous, for your Godd you have made, and your Images, and Idols, and Fables? And have you not tewed your ſelves about them, as much as ever <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> did about the godds they made? For the Spirit of God is Gentle and Meek, and ſo your <hi>Phanatick</hi> Humours have ſufficienly ſpoken forth themſelves to the Nations.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſpeakeſt, <hi>That we have rightly tituled the Mother Church of</hi> Rome <hi>the Old-Woman:</hi> ☞ Though thou haſt got ſome Glory in it, which ſeems to paint thee off a little, but thou ſhouldſt have taken all our words, The Mother Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with all her Old-Womans Fables; this thou tearmeſt to be a Scoff: But is it not a Scoff in thee to call us the <hi>Young Woman,</hi> for calling that the <hi>Mother Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>the Old Woman,</hi> with her <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> that Harlot who hath drunk the Blood of the Saints and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Jeſus; ſhe hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onour from God, nor her ſaints; and her Reward will be the Flames, and all that hold her up, the Flames of Hell; read in the <hi>Revelation</hi> her Portion: And there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon between your <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>Old Woman</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> that you cry up ſo; and Chriſt Jeſus, the Saviour, and the true Church; but it manifeſts your Ignorance and Darkneſs, and as them that call Darkneſs Light, and Light Darkneſs; Good Evil, and Evil Good: And your Mother <hi>Rome</hi> doth begin to be out of date, and is out of date with many that are come to Chriſt Jeſus, their Head, the true Church; and do lay her aſide like an old <hi>Almanack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt, becauſe we call her the Old Woman of <hi>Rome,</hi> this was enough to convince us of our Arguments. Nay, nay, ſhe is a Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, and not the Spouſe of Chriſt; you ſpeak as men that have loſt your brains: For though we do ſay the Old Woman, with all her Fables; yet we deny her to be the Spouſe of Chriſt Jeſus, for ſhe hath ſhed the <hi>Blood</hi> of the Martyrs and is brim full of Idolatry, and her Cup is full of Abominations, which corrupt the Earth; and to the Brim ſhe muſt have a Cup of Indignation of the Wrath of the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
            <p>And as for the Weather-cocks, blown about with every rew and falſe doctrine, look into your own Fields, and look at <hi>Rome:</hi> How many falſe Doctrines have blown you about, and falſe Wayes, and ſeveral Images, and Orders, have you ſet up ſince the Apoſtles dayes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49487:11"/>by that perſecuting murdering ſpirit? Do not you call your old Maſs-houſe, your Church? Do not you Worſhip there? And when you come into them, do not you put off your Hats? And do not you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip when your Hoſt is carried, and fall upon your knees, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip your Image? Is not here your Church, founded upon Idolatry? And did not the Apoſtles ſpeak of your Antiquity, and worſhipping of Angels, and that were Intruders into thoſe things that they did not ſee, that did not hold the Head, and neglect the Body; and ſo you are Worſhippers of Angels, and neglect the Head, and have ſet up a Head of your own making. And have not the Gates of <hi>Hell</hi> prevailed againſt your outward Houſe, which you call a Church, and your People.</p>
            <p>Now you ſeem to ſhuffle, and call the People your Chruch, and ſay, <hi>The Gates of Hell hath not prevailed againſt your Church, that is, againſt your People: The Reaſon,</hi> you ſay, <hi>is. The Spirit of Truth, Chriſt ſaith, ſhall lead his Church into a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, which he would ſend to them: And Chriſts ſaying to</hi> Peter, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock will I build my Church: And therefore becauſe Christ ſaid theſe words to his Diſciples, therefore the Gates of Hell hath not prevailed against your Church, and your Church hath ſtood without Interruption to this preſent day, neither Fails nor Corrupts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark People, how impudent theſe Men are! What without bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they can ſpeak ſuch words: Is not all their Brothel-houſe, and Stew-houſes, and Fornication, and Adultery, is not this Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? And all their Idols, and Images, from their falſe Church, ſilled to the brim with that? And all their bloody Perſecutions, is not this from an unclean ſpirit? But he ſaith, <hi>Their Church hath ſtood without the leaſt Interruption:</hi> And now people, you know that ſince <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, the firſt Univerſal Pope, was ſet up by a Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, one <hi>Phocas,</hi> who Murdered his Maſter; and ſince their Church hath been held up by Murder; he ſaith, <hi>That their Church hath ſtood without the leaſt Interruption:</hi> Now ſince the Pope got up, did not the <hi>Turk</hi> get up? And did not the <hi>Turk</hi> get from the <hi>Pope, Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Conſtantinople, Aegypt, Greece,</hi> and many other Parts of the World, that might be mentioned? How can theſe men be ſo audati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to ſay, Their Church hath ſtood without Interruption; And if the <hi>Turk</hi> be the Gates of Hell, he hath prevailed againſt you: And are there not <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>France?</hi> Yea, at <hi>Rome; Proteſtants</hi> in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49487:11"/>
               <hi>Switzerland, Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> and many Princes, as King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> King of <hi>Sweedeland,</hi> and Low-Countries, and <hi>Ireland, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and other places which have forſaken the Pope and his Church, in words. Now have not the Gates of Hell prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt this People? Have not theſe <hi>Papists</hi> loſt their Reaſon and Underſtanding, as men? What, hath not the godd of the World blinded you, that you cannot ſee? Oh that men ſhould be ſo blind, and ſo bold, to utter ſuch Falſhood, as to ſay, <hi>That it hath been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt Interruption;</hi> the Pope and falſe Church! Nay, it is their City that hath been divided: what I yars are theſe I that love to Lye, to Flatter, and Diſſemble on this manner, and to Deceive the Simple; they are ſimple indeed that will be deceived. Alas, alas, You are driven up into a narrow ſcantling, over you were at firſt. Did not you Burn with Fire and Fagot in <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Bonner</hi>'s time? If theſe be the Gates of Hell, they have prevailed againſt you, and your counterfeit Church too, and your Head alſo: And it hath been the unclean Ghoſt that came from the Dragon, that hath led you into all theſe Images, and Idolatry, and Sedition, and Blackneſs, and Darkneſs, which is over you. We know that Chriſt did pray to the Father, and he hath ſent the Spirit of Truth, that leads the true Church into all Truth, of which Church Chriſt is the Head.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſpeakeſt, <hi>Of</hi> Peters <hi>Feeding his Lambs and Sheep;</hi> you have torn the Sheep in pieces, and Lambs alſo, and rul'd by Force and Cruelty, and ſed the Wolves; <hi>and</hi> Peter <hi>having Power to Bind</hi> (and ſo did the reſt of the Apoſtles) <hi>and to Looſe:</hi> What is this to your counterfeit Church, whom the Gates of Hell hath prevailed againſt? And a great ſtir you make to hold up the Pope, your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Head: And you cavel at that in the <hi>Acts,</hi> of <hi>Peter</hi>'s being ſent by the Diſciples to Preach, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. for you would fain have <hi>Peter</hi> a Pope, that you may hold up your Pope; and this clearly proves that <hi>Peter</hi> was not above his Brethren: but they were all Brethren, as Chriſt ſaid, they were his Brethren; you abuſe Chriſts words in ſaying that he made him the greateſt, and Head; for Chriſt tells his Diſciples all his True Church are Brethren: But doth thy Chriſt, that is made of Bread and Wine, tell thee that <hi>Peter</hi> was Head? And ſo you will make a Head of the Pope, and your Pope and you will be Pead of your chriſt, that you have made; and Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, when they were at Striſe who ſhould be counted greateſt, Chriſt tells
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49487:12"/>them, <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles exerciſe Lordſhip over them, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over them, and are called Gratious Lords; it muſt not be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you.</hi> Here you ſlight Chriſt's words, in making a Head, and ſetting up your Gratious Lords, your Popes, to exerciſe Lordſhip over the People, in diſpite againſt Chriſts Command; and ſo plainly manifeſt an Antichriſt, a Schiſmatick, and a Sect degenerated from the true Brotherhood, and true Head; and he that will be the Greateſt muſt be as the Leaſt, he that is Chiefeſt as he that Serveth, &amp;c. and ſo he brings to an even rule: And in many places it is plain that <hi>Peter</hi> never took the Headſhip to himſelf, as your counterfeit Head hath done in oppoſition to the True Church, and true Chriſt, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite againſt him; and this makes no Contradiction; for the Chiefeſt muſt be as he that Serveth, and the Greateſt as the Leaſt; this cuts off your Lordſhip; for the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> were reproved for that: And thou bringeſt an Argument to prove that <hi>Peter</hi> was Head of the Apoſtles, though the Apoſtles ſent him.</p>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Though the Father ſent the Son, yet to ſay that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath greater Power then the Son,</hi> thou ſayeſt, <hi>is Blaſphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt ſaith of Him, <hi>That his Father is Greater then He,</hi> John 14.28. and that was no Blaſphemy in Chriſt: And how was he Greater, was it not in Power? Yet we tell thee again, that the Father and Son is one according to his Divinity; he is God, and God was in Chriſt; and according to the Fleſh he Suffered, it was not God that Suffered, that Died, the Eternal God, but Chriſt Suffered according to the Fleſh, as the Scripture declares: for what God was, that Chriſt prayed to, and ſaid, <hi>Father, if it be poſſible, let this Cup paſs from me; but not my Will but they Will:</hi> But theſe things are a Myſtery to you, and your dark ſpirits, who it ſeems are ignorant of the Scriptures, neither are the Holy Men of Gods words fit to come into your Mouths.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſayeſt, <hi>Christ would have I relates to be humble People.</hi> Look over the Popes Church, and what Humility do you ſee? Are not your Women full of Spots, and the Pope with his Trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-Crown, and their Gorgious Attire? Was this like <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of Jeſus, who was brought to Bed in a Stable, and laid Jeſus in the Mainger? Now we ſhall hardly have room in your Stable, but in your Fires and Inquiſitions; for the Devil would Deſtroy True Chriſtianity throughout the Earth, who is become a falſe Chriſtian in you; but Chriſt will brake the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And if <hi>Peter</hi> was at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49487:12"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi> yet he was not Pope over all the Churches, nor any of his Diſciples, nor none of <hi>Peters</hi> Follower; all theſe things will not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your Seditious Head, nor this Catalogue of Biſhops, that were ſet up, not for the firſt Six Hundred Years after Chriſt, there was no U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Pope all that time, till, as I ſaid before, <hi>Boniface</hi> the third was ſet up by <hi>Phocas</hi> the Murderer; and after came in the <hi>Turk;</hi> and then came in the Devil, that hath filled your Cup to the brim with a Raging ſpirit, and a Murdering ſpirit And thou ſayeſt the truth of this Succeſſion is gathered out of <hi>Matthew,</hi> which proves nothing at all of this to you; for your counterfeit Church hath been prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt by them which worſhip <hi>Mahomet:</hi> Chriſt was with <hi>Peter</hi> to the end of his dayes, and with all them that be in his Spirit, the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus. But what is this to you who have erred from <hi>Peter</hi>'s Spirit, and are got into a Murderous ſpirit, who Perſecute People to Death for your Rudiments; <hi>Peter</hi> did not Perſecute Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for not owning Chriſt, nor for not following Idols, or images, the Works of mens hands.</p>
            <p>Another falſe Cover theſe Papiſts have, which they daub People with, concerning <hi>Peters</hi> being Head of the Church, where it is ſaid in <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. where Chriſt asked his Diſciples, <hi>Whom do men ſay that I am?</hi> And their Anſwer was, <hi>That he was</hi> John Baptiſt, <hi>ſome ſay; and others</hi> Elias; <hi>and others,</hi> Jeremiah, <hi>or one of the Prophets:</hi> But he ſaid, <hi>Whom do you ſay that I am?</hi> Peter ſaid. <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Son of the Living God: And Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto him, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed art thou</hi> Simon Barjona: <hi>for Fleſh and Blood hath not revealed this to thee: I ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y unto thee, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u art</hi> Peter; <hi>and upon this Rock I will build my Church, and the Gates of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi> Now if this Church had been built upon <hi>Peter,</hi> as he was a man of Fleſh and Blood, as you ſay; then when <hi>Peter</hi> was put to Death, the Gates of Hell had prevai'ed then; and here the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would give Chriſt the Lye; but Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That Fleſh and Blood had not revealed this to thee; and thou art</hi> Peter; <hi>and upon this Rock will I build my Church:</hi> That his Fleſh and Blood had not revealed unto him; thou art <hi>Peter:</hi> And what ſignifies <hi>Peter?</hi> If <hi>Peter</hi> ſignifies a <hi>Rock;</hi> and if Chriſt built his Church upon the ſignification of <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sur-name, which ſignifies but an outward Rock, which outward Rock may be brought as a Figure of Chriſt, or a Parable, or Compariſon; if it be built upon the Parable, it is not built upon the thing it ſelf: Muſt not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49487:13"/>then all your Popes names be call'd <hi>Peter,</hi> if they be the Rocks of your Church; and ſo your Church muſt be built upon their Sur-names: Now if it be built upon <hi>Peter</hi> as a man, and your <hi>Popes</hi> as men, as you ſay it is, as Fleſh, and Blood, &amp;c. then it is built upon the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the word <hi>Man,</hi> which is not the ſignification of <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sur-name; but the ſignification of <hi>Man,</hi> is <hi>Adam;</hi> for <hi>Son of Man</hi> is <hi>Son of Adam,</hi> as <hi>Ben Adam, Ben Elohim</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> ſignifies <hi>Red Earth,</hi> does it not? And ſo the Interpretation of the Popes Rock is, <hi>That he built his Church upon Red Earth;</hi> and Red Earth is not a Rock.</p>
            <p>And what is that which Fleſh and Blood hath not revealed? Thou art Chriſt the Son of the Living God, and upon this Rock is Chriſt's Church built, that his Fleſh and Blood had not revealed, and the Gates of Hell ſhall not preva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l againſt this Rock, Chriſt Jeſus; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes the Devil, and his works, and his Power is over Hell and Death; and they are Living Stones that be Members of his Body. What is all this to the Popes counterfeit Head and Church, which the Gates of Hell have prevail'd againſt, their fleſhly Foundation, their fleſhly Church, and their carnal Head, which is deviliſh: And thus they have erred and degenerated from the Foundation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtles, and Chriſt Jeſus, being the Top and Corner-Stone; for Chriſt was their Rock the Apoſtles confeſſed; and the Rock that followed the <hi>Jews</hi> was Chriſt: And ſo it is clear, that you are the Fooliſh Builders, that have built your Houſe on the Sand, the Sea ſhore, and many of your Houſes are walled down; for they that built up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Rock Chriſt Jeſus, which Fleſh and Blood hath not revealed, but the Father hath revealed that <hi>Rock</hi> which his Church is built upon; by his Power and by his Spirit they ſtand ſure: Glory be to God forever.</p>
            <p>And whereas you bring <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. verſ. 26, 27, 28. and compare it to <hi>John</hi> 6.5. This you do bring to prove your Sacrament of the Alter, and your chriſt and godd, that is made of Bread and Wine, which is to no purpoſe at all; for that of <hi>John</hi> 6. where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Your Fathers did eat Manna in the Wilderneſs, but are dead:</hi> So you have eaten your godd that you have made with Bread and Wine, and are dead: But Chriſt is the true Bread, which comes down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; for Bread comes from the Corn and Wine from the Grape, and that comes from below; but he that eateth this Bread, that comes dow from Heaven, ſhall live for ever, &amp;c. he that doth eat Chriſts
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49487:13"/>Fleſh and drink his Blood, doth not eat it Figuratively, but they eat it Really, if they have life in him: And Chriſts Fleſh is not Wafers, nor his Blood is not outward Wine, that comes from the Grape; but Chriſt ſaith, <hi>His words are Spirit and Life, &amp; the Fleſh profitteth nothing; for it is the Spirit that quickeneth:</hi> Therefore you are darker then the <hi>Jews,</hi> and cannot receive Chriſts words, but judge them carnally, as they did: And for your old Fathers Talk or Story, that proves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to us, but is like your own Fables. And as for that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. proves nothing as for you, that make a chriſt and a godd of Bread and Wine, for they wrote, <hi>That they were to take it in Remembrance of Chriſt:</hi> and if a Remembrance of him, then it was not he: Have you loſt your Reaſon? If thou doeſt any thing in Remembrance of a man, if it be the man, what, doeſt thou it in Rememembrance of him? He ſaith, <hi>As often as you do this, do it in Remembrance of Chriſt;</hi> as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as you eat this Bread: And ſo both the Bread and the Cup was left unto them as Often, not Alwayes; for they were to injoy <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> And he ſaid he would come and dwell in them; and ſo had it been he. Chriſt, it had been Non-ſence and Ridiculous to ſay, in Remembrance of him, when it was he: What ſilly reaſoning is this? And you do ſhew forth his Death till he come; ſo ſaith he, <hi>Till he come;</hi> Mark, then it is not he, it is not Chriſt; for if he is to come, it is not the ſame Chriſt as was offered up upon the Croſs, if he be riſen, and he is to come; So you have been all the unworthy Eaters and Drinkers, and not diſcern Chriſt nor his Body, who have put your Bread and Wine for the Body of Chriſt; and ſo have eaten and drunk your own Damnation, not diſcerning the Lords Body; and therefore you are Sick, and Weak, and aſleep in your Sins: That which is done in a Shew, is it not a Figure, or a Shaddow? And a Shaddow mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be done away when the Subſtance is come: And people muſt come to dye with Chriſt, and be buried with him, if they live with him, and not alwayes eating (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.) and drinking in Remembrance of him Bread and Wine; and they muſt Suffer with him, and Dye with him, and be Buried with him and Riſe with him; now if you be riſen with Chriſt, you ſeek thoſe things that come from above; for Bread, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Wine is from be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow: For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the Door,</hi> doth not be? And he is the Way, he is the Vine, and he is a Rock, and a Stone: And is Chriſt an outward Stone, an outward Vine, outward Bread, and outward Water, an outward Door, an outward Rock?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49487:14"/>If thou interpreteſt the one, interpret the other, and confute thy ſelf, which is enough to confute all your whole counterfeit Church. Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may eat and drink natural bread and natural wine without Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to themſelves: But ſurely the Bread and the Wine, which you ſay is Chriſt, and his Blood, and his Fleſh, and the whole chriſt, a Wafer, or ſup of Wine, or a piece of Bread, any Drunkard or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Man or Woman, that is, can ſee it with their outward Eyes; but to ſay that to be Chriſt, his Fleſh, and his Blood, that came down from Heaven, which came from the Grape, and from the Corn; thou wouldſt make people believe, as the <hi>Phyloſopher, That Snow is Black, and the Sun abroad Plate of Mettal.</hi> And your Confecrations makes your Wafers and Bread no more Chriſt, then it was before, nor God; for it is Blaſphemy in you to ſay, That Wafers, or a little Bread or Wine is God: You have made many godds, and eaten them, and drunk them; but except your ſimple people had been inchanted, and ſo you make them believe it to be God; but we are over your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, and in that which will Grind you to Powder; and we know that Chriſt hath given his Fleſh for the Life of the World, that is a Myſtery to you, that make Chriſts of Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>Moreover, you ſay, <hi>That the Body of Chriſt was given for to redeem our Sins upon the Croſs, which Body he gave to his Diſciples at his Laſt Supper, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> People, did you ever hear the like? What ſilly <hi>Logick</hi> or <hi>Rhetorick</hi> is this? It ſeems the Apoſtles eat Chriſts Body, and drunk his Blood; then what Body had Chriſt to offer upon the Croſs? Had he two Bodies; for he ſaith, <hi>He redeemed their Sins with his Body upon the Croſs;</hi> and before he ſaith, <hi>He had given his Body to his Diſciples, and they did eat it after Supper?</hi> What Non-ſence and Confuſion is this! It may well be called <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> that taught him ſuch a Leſſon: After the Diſciples had eaten his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and drunk his Blood, when he went to be offered up upon the Croſs, which he ſaith, His Body was offered up upon the Croſs, for the redeeming of their ſins: Did you ever hear ſuch Doctrine? Did Chriſt come to redeem the Sins of people? You read of the true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that the Apoſtles came to turn people from Darkneſs to Light; but you never heard of ſuch a Doctrine; Sin is of the Devil: Did
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49487:14"/>Chriſt come to Redeem the Devil? Nay: He came to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, and to Redeem People from Sin: See what groſs Deluſion and blind Ignorance appears here from this Seditious Sect of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and theſe that ſtile themſelves <hi>Maſters of Arts:</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, The ſame Body that ſuffered upon the Croſs, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles eat; and upon this their Salvation hangs: Now if the Apoſtles had eaten it, and drunk his Blood, then what Body had he to offer? Or ſee what Salvation theſe people have, which hang upon the Bread and Wine after Conſecrated, to be Chriſt, and have no Chriſt but that which they make; <hi>And that is it which ſuffered upon the Croſs:</hi> Then how came he to riſe again, if they had eaten him, that very Body after Supper, that very Body of Chriſt Jeſus? And how came he to be laid in the Grave, and yet came after to ſhew the Apoſtles his Hands and Sides, ſeeing they had eaten him, and his Body was whole? And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>As often as you do eat this Bread, and drink this Cup;</hi> Was it an outward Cup they drunk, or was there ſomewhat in the Cup? Did they ſwollow an outward Cup? Come, interpret this, and confute your ſelves.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou bringeſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and ſpeakeſt ſcoffingly of the People of God (called <hi>Quakers</hi>) and call'ſt them Humming Speakers, and ſheweſt thy ſelf to be of <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> brood: And you bring St. <hi>John Damaſcenus,</hi> and a many ſuch like Fathers of the Church, which is nothing to the purpoſe, but only to blind People (that are ignorant) withal, to make them believe that your Bread and Wine is Chriſt after you have bleſſed it, to keep your poor deceived people in ignorance: But the Lord is taking off your Covers, that your filthy Raggs may be ſeen, and your ugly Images and Idols, which have been ſet up by the Unclean ſpirit, and ſpirit of Perſecution.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou layeſt down a Charge, <hi>To know who was our firſt grand Speaker, after</hi> Peter, <hi>of our Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Anſwer,</hi> He that was of <hi>Peter</hi>'s Spirit, which was of the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, which was the Seed of the Woman, whom the Beaſt, and your falſe Church, the Whore, hath drunk their Flood, and made War againſt them that have kept the Teſtimony of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, that have ſeen all your works and actions, and teſtifie againſt them, with all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49487:15"/>the whole Train of Idolatry, and Idols, and Images, that you have made an Idol of, Bread and Wine; and now the Seed is riſing, and the Witneſs, that will make your earth to quake; and Chriſt ſays, <hi>Learn of Me;</hi> he was the firſt Speaker to us, called <hi>Quakers; This is my beloved Son, hear ye him,</hi> ſaith God: So I tell thee, he was our firſt Speaker, and he hath given us his Spirit, <hi>that leads into all Truth,</hi> that hath taught us the Way to life and Salvation; and he is the Rock of Ages, and not <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Foundation of many Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and is the ſame to day as he was yeſterday, and ſo forever; and he hath been our Leader, our Prophet, our Shepherd, our Prieſt, our Biſhop, our Councellor, our Miniſter, our Preacher, whom God hath anointed to Preach, that Preacheth Life, Light, and Salvation: So we come to obey his Doctrine, and do his Will, and we ſhall know his Doctrine; if in doing the ſame, you will know our firſt Preacher, you muſt come to the Light, to ſee him, which will condemn all the Images and Idols, and condemn your chriſt and godd, that you make of bread and wine; and condemn your head and church too.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſpeakeſt Scoffingly, <hi>Of the Church of God being Smothered under a Cloud?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſay, to theſe Mockers, and to this Seditious Sect, That the <hi>Church</hi> hath been in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> there fed of God Forty and Two Moneths, One Thouſand Two Hundred and Threeſcore Dayes, which is a Time, and Times, and half a Time; ſo count you a day for a year, and then you may reckon your ſelves how long your falſe church the <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> hath been on the back of the Beaſt, whom the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> the <hi>Dragon</hi> gives power to and the year when the Woman, the true <hi>Church,</hi> is coming-out of the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> who hath been fed of God: God hath been her Feeder, which indeed you with the Dragons pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er would have ſmothered Her, as under a Cloud or a Tubb, but the Earth helped Her; and ſhe was preſerved in the Wilderneſs, where you could not find <hi>her,</hi> though you went with <hi>Judas his Swords, Staves</hi> and <hi>Lanthorns,</hi> &amp; your band of <hi>Soulaiers</hi> from your counterfeit Head: But I tell you, <hi>She was fed of God in the Wilderneſs Ferty two Moneths;</hi> and reckon this, and then you may ſee how long the falſe church, and the whore and the beaſt hath reigned, and when ſhe comes out of the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> again.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49487:15"/>
            <p>Then we Challenge you, <hi>To tell us how many Martyrs, Prophets, and Saints, the beaſt, and whore, the falſe church, that ſate upon the Beaſt, in the Dragons power; how much of their Flood have they drunk, to wit, the Blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus? And ſo by this time thou wilt ſee the coming in of the Falſe church the where; and the going into the Wilderneſs of the true Church; the Down-fall of the Beaſt, and of the Whore; for if thou canſt count the number of the true Church, that comes out of the Wilderneſs, thou wilt know the number of your falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scriptures we own; we do contend againſt your filthy Raggs of your Hereſie, which we deny, and will not put on; for we have a better <hi>Garment,</hi> which is the <hi>Fine Linnen,</hi> which is the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THe</hi> Ingenious Reader <hi>hath read your Paper, and here is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in Anſwer to it; and finds it a confuſed piece of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and Toutologies, and Contradictions; and if all the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, and theſe that thou haſt quoted, be as dark as you are, they are in that which is Darkneſs it ſelf, and ignorant of the Scripture, and of Chriſt, and the Apoſtles Doctrine, and Spirit and, Power, and Faith, and are ſeperated and degenerated from it (to wit) the Spirit of God: You are all judged, you and your Forefathers, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with your Works, your Images; and are in the ſpirit of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, the firſt birth of the Fleſh; of</hi> Hagar, <hi>that is caſt out, and and not the Bride of the Lambs Wife, nor the true Spouſe of Chriſt Jeſus, which is coming forth of the Wilderneſs.</hi> Halelujah.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49487:16"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>IN <hi>Matt.</hi> 26: Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Take the Cup,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Drink ye all of it:</hi> Now was it an outward Cup that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples did drink, or ſomething in the Cup? Then you do interpret this wrong; for it was not the Cup they did drink.</p>
            <p>And then you muſt interpret that Scripture <hi>[This is my Body, and Chriſt brake the outward Bread]</hi> then did Chriſt break his own Body, and give it to his Diſciples before he ſuffered: and did they eat it then? What Body had Chriſt to offer upon the Croſs for the Sins of the People, if that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had eaten it? And Chriſt doth not ſay, The Wine which was called the Blood of the New Teſtament, was the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Mark</hi> 14. <hi>and Luke</hi> 22. <hi>Chriſt brake the Bread, and gave it to his Diſciples:</hi> And did he break his Body that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered upon the Croſs for Mankind? No: His Body was whole then: <hi>And he took the Bread and brake it, and gave it to the Diſciples, and they did eat it:</hi> For if that outward Wine was his Blood, and the Bread his Body, then his Blood and Body was eaten and drunk before he ſuffered; and if his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples had eaten his Body, and drunk his Blood, then they had eaten Chriſt; and then there had been no Offering on the Croſs for the Sins of Mankind, according to your <hi>Aſſertion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt.</hi> 26. <hi>Mark</hi> 14. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>For I ſay unto you, I will not any more eat thereof, until it be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49487:16"/>
            <p>Lule 22. <hi>For I ſay unto you, I will not drink of the Fruit of the Vine, until the Kingdom of God ſhall come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark 14. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, I will drink no more of the of the Fruit of the Vine, until that day that I drink it new in the Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>But I ſay unto you, I will not drink henceforth of this Fruit of the Vine, until that day when I drink it new in the Fathers Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What! Will Chriſt drink his own Blood with his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples new in his Fathers Kingdom, and eat of the Bread, his own Body, in the Kingdom of God?</p>
            <p>And did Chriſt eat his own body, and drink his own Blood while he was on the Earth with his Diſciples? for he ſaith, <hi>I will no more drink, &amp; I will not any more eat, until it be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God; and I will no more drink until that day</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that I drink it new in my Fathers Kingdom.</hi> And what doth NO MORE ſignifie? Doth it not ſignifie that he had eaten and drunk it before? And what then do you ſay, or affirm, that he had eaten his own Body, and drunk his own Blood? Come, let us ſee what ſenſe you will make of this, with all your Keys?</p>
            <p>And what did the Paſcal-Lamb typifie forth, your outward Bread and Wine? And what did one outward thing Type forth another outward thing? And what did Chriſt eat him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and drink himſelf? and did the Apoſtles eat Chriſt before he ſuffered? Is this your Doctrine? Did not the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lamb Typifie our Paſchal Lamb, CHRIST, our Paſſover? And what did it type forth your Bread, and Wine, chriſt, which you made, which is outward, and from the ground? And there your Heads go downward, and the one outward thing types forth another outward thing; and this is your Doctrine; is it not? and ſo that one Natural Types forth another.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49487:17"/>
            <p>But we tell you, That Chriſt, our Paſcal-Lamb, endeth the <hi>Jews</hi> Paſcal-Lamb, and their Paſſover; for he is the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of them, which were Types of him, who is the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Man, who endeth them all, that were Types and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of him.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>For we being many are one Bread and one Body, &amp;c.</hi> and what was this, the outward bread? and were the Apoſtles and Saints Bodies, outward bread? Or were the Saints the Body of Chriſt, and he their Head; and ſo one Body, and one Head.</p>
            <p>Or hath Chriſt ever a Body, but what you do make of Bread and Wine? Anſwer.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>That the Bread, and the Cup, was the Communion of the Body of Chriſt.</hi> And he doth not ſay, <hi>That the Bread is the Body of Chriſt;</hi> nor doth he ſay, <hi>That the Cup is Chriſt's Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And wherein doth your Cup and Table differ from the Cup and Table of Devils? Anſwer: And come let us ſee what ſence you will make of this, you Corrupters and Deſtroyers of Scriptures, the Maſters of all Corruptions, Theft, and Plunder; the Devils Eſpouſe, and a Help meet; who with his Sparks ſetteth Princes together by the Ears; this uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dragon would have brought the Earth to deſolation, who with his fiery Sparks, which he hath thrown amongſt the Nations, hath ſet the Nations on fire, and would have all bow to him, and Perſecutes them that bows to God.</p>
            <p>And are not you offering up your chriſt (in every Nation and Country where you have power) which you make of your Bread and Wine? And without bluſhing falſly call your ſelves Miniſters of the True Chriſt, but you are the Miniſters of that chriſt you make of Bread and Wine: So you <hi>make</hi> your <hi>Lord,</hi> your <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and your <hi>Hoſt;</hi> and then you do offer him in every Country or Nation; and ſo you make many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49487:17"/>of godds and chriſts, and many thouſand godd and chriſt Hoſt-makers you are, &amp; many thouſand Offerings ye offer up Yearly. But the <hi>True Chriſt</hi> is offered up <hi>Once for All,</hi> and not <hi>yearly:</hi> And this was the true <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſts Doctrine, who denyed the <hi>Yearly Sacrifices</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> which Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>True Offering</hi> ends; and ſo Chriſt put away ſin by the offering of himſelf; and ſo our <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> was not made by man, but he was begotten of God, who is made higher then the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and whom God did prepare a <hi>Body.</hi> And you make your body and blood of your Antichriſt, and offer him up <hi>Yearly</hi> to deceive the People, and keep them in their ſin, and then tell them of a <hi>Purgatory when they are Dead;</hi> GREAT DECEIVERS; and ſo you do the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>Devil, your godd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he that did the Will of the <hi>Living God</hi> (to wit, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) did it through the <hi>Offering up of his Body Once for All;</hi> and ſo there is an end of the <hi>Offerings,</hi> and your falſe ones, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with your <hi>chriſts,</hi> the workmanſhip of your own hands, which you have cauſed people to worſhip, both Small and Great; <hi>a Mark of the great Whore,</hi> ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>And you <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who ſay, <hi>you make the body and blood of your chriſt;</hi> and when that you have made it you ſay, <hi>people muſt not have the blood, but the body of your chriſt, you have made. If that this was the True Chriſt, as it is the Falfe,</hi> then you keep all your Deceived People in Death, and from <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification; For except they eat Chriſts Fleſh, and drink his Blood, they have no Life in them;</hi> and this comes down from above, and is not from below; as your <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>fleſh,</hi> which you make of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine;</hi> and ſo they muſt drink the <hi>Blood,</hi> as well as eat the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of Chriſt, if they have Life: and they that do not drink his <hi>Blood,</hi> have not Life in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for all the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do drink his <hi>Blood,</hi> and have Life, and they are juſtified and cleanſed with his <hi>Blood,</hi> and their <hi>Faith</hi> is in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49487:18"/>the <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt; and ſo all that have Life, <hi>Commune in both kinds;</hi> that is, <hi>They eat the Fleſh of Chriſt, and drink his Blood,</hi> which no man can make, but it comes down from above.</p>
            <p>But you that are dead, and in Death, who have gotten the Name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and pretend to make a chriſt of <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> of <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine,</hi> which is but a Lye, yet you will not give your people your <hi>blood,</hi> which you have made of <hi>wine;</hi> and ſo according to your own <hi>doctrine</hi> your people are <hi>dead,</hi> if you do profeſs the <hi>Scripture;</hi> for Chriſt doth not ſeparate the <hi>fleſh</hi> from the <hi>blood,</hi> but the one muſt be received as the other; and Chriſt doth not limit it from any one, but did ſhed his Blood for all men; but this is your <hi>Cheat</hi> of <hi>Pope, Cardinals,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who love the Wine to drink it; and thus you do deceive your people.</p>
            <p>And alſo when you have made your <hi>lord,</hi> and <hi>hoſt,</hi> and <hi>chriſt,</hi> you do adore him, and worſhip him, and reverence him and cauſe the people to do the ſame; and then when you have done, you do EAT up your GOD, HOST, LORD, and CHRIST, which you have adored, reverenced, and worſhipped. Oh Deceit! This is worſe then the <hi>Heathen;</hi> for never do you read in any <hi>Chronicle,</hi> that the <hi>Heathen</hi> did ſo <hi>Eat</hi> any of the <hi>Godds</hi> that they had made with their hands, as you have done; and thus you diſpiſe the true <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and confine him in the <hi>Creatures</hi> of Bread and Wine; all which (of your works) are for Judgment.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49487:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
